Good morning. Today's דף, daf, we're going to do the בבלי; Bavli;
today's דף daf is ל"ד. Lamed. We pick up on the bottom
of כ"ט עמוד ב'. Chaf Tes Amud Beis. No, in the בבלי,
Bavli, we are doing, we're behind. We are doing, what do you
call? We're in the middle of a whole discussion about witnesses
and what type of an admission constitutes a binding admission, and when
you have empowered the witnesses to go ahead and to write a
שטר shtar against you to create a שטר shtar to testify to
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says at the bottom of
כ"ט עמוד ב' Chaf Tes Amud Beis the following: ההיא אודיתא דלא
הוה כתב ביה אמר לנא כתבו וחתומו והבו ליה. Hahee udisa de-lo
hava katav bayeh, amar lanan kisvu v'chasmu v'havu lei. So there was
a שטר shtar that was written that somebody had admitted to a
debt,
but the שטר shtar didn't say that he authorized us the עדים
eydim to write the שטר. shtar. And we just learned before that
the עדים eydim have to be authorized to write the שטר; shtar;
they cannot create a שטר. shtar. So what's the story? אביי ורבא
דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye v'Rava d'amri duvayhu, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both
say, היינו דריש לקיש. hinu d'Reish Lakish. We should apply the principle
of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש חזקה אין עדים חותמים
על השטר אלא אם כן נעשה גדול. D'amar Reish Lakish chazaka ein
eydim chomtim al hashtar ela im kein na'aseh gadol. So there's an
issue if you have a שטר shtar that was written that somebody
sold land, and there's a principle in בבא בתרא Bava Basra that
somebody has to be 20 years old to sell ancestral lands, and
there's a question how old he was, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava
says we can assume that the witnesses did the right thing. If
you have a שטר, shtar, we'll assume they wouldn't have signed it
unless the person was a גדול. gadol. So here too, we should
assume that the witnesses would not have created a שטר shtar unless
they had been authorized to do so. So מתקיף לה רב פפא,
maskif lah Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa challenged this. ואי
תימא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמידי דאנן לא ידעינן. Vee teima
Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua amee gamidee d'anan lo yadeina. Is there
could be something that we to us ourselves is not so obvious?
Meaning we just had a whole discussion earlier in the גמרא Gemara
whether the witnesses have to be, you know, authorized or not. So
it wasn't black and white to us. This was like a, you
know, a whole חידוש chiddush as it were, that you know, when
do witnesses have to be authorized to write a שטר, shtar, when
not. So this is a matter that's a little bit that's vague
to us. וספרי דבי דינא ידעי? V'safrei d'bei dina yadi? And you
think that the scribes just automatically know this stuff? So meaning if
assume that somebody said admitted in front of a witness, and then
the מלווה malveh said, okay, let's go write a שטר, shtar, and
he took the witnesses to write a שטר, shtar, who would be
the gatekeeper? Who would be the person that would know, wait, you
can't write a שטר shtar unless you've been authorized? So maybe it
could be the עדים, eydim, but עדים, eydim, you know, you get
random people to be your עדים. eydim. So presumably you're going to
expect the סופר sofer to be the gatekeeper and say, wait a
minute, I can't write a שטר shtar unless the עדים eydim have
been authorized. So רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying, we can't assume
סופרים sofrim know this הלכה halacha that you have to be authorized
after there's been an admission to write a שטר. shtar. So if
we can't assume that סופרים sofrim know this, and the language is
not explicit in the שטר shtar that they've been authorized, we have
to assume that the שטר shtar was written without authorization and it's
not a valid שטר. shtar.
I know that's in בבא בתרא
Bava Basra and they pass. I know. So that's what's going to
happen too here. So the גמרא Gemara says, שיילנו לספרי דאביי וידעי.
shalvnu l'safrei d'Abaye v'yadi. So they actually went and they, you know,
quizzed אביי's Abaye scribes, and they knew, no, no, no, you don't
write a שטר shtar unless it's been authorized. לספרי דרבא וידעי, L'safrei
d'Rava v'yadi, and רבא's Rava scribes and they knew. And it's אביי
Abaye and רבא Rava who self, who they themselves say we can
assume that the scribes know what they're doing. Okay, now of course
it's a little bit of like a rigged test, not really rigged,
but whatever, biased test, because אביי Abaye and רבא's Rava scribes know.
Okay, does everybody else's scribes know? Who knows? But this is the
גמרא's Gemara point that even though you need to be authorized and
we should, we'd like to see the language of authorization in the
שטר, shtar, if it's missing that language, we can assume that they
were authorized and they did it properly. Okay. ההיא אודיתא דהוה כתב
ביה, Hahee udisa d'havi kasav bayeh, now there was a שטר shtar
that had an admission and it was written in the שטר shtar
and it said: דוכרן פתגמי, duchran pisgamei, a remembrance of events, meaning
it recorded events that occurred. וכל לישני דבי דינא, V'chol lishnei d'bei
dina, and all the normal way the בית דין beis din writes,
meaning the way witnesses would write a שטר shtar would be אנן
סהדי, anan sahadi, we testify, היכי, eich, how the following event occurred.
The way a בית דין beis din would write a שטר shtar
would be less that we testify the event occurred and it would
be a slightly different type of, I don't know the exact נוסח,
nusach, but the נוסח nusach more would be like, you know, the
following things took place in front of us, as opposed to we
testify that. Okay, so it would be a slightly different language that
would be used. And all the other types of languages that reflected
the idea that were signals that this was a שטר shtar of
בית דין beis din and not a שטר shtar of עדים. eydim.
Now the benefit of being a שטר shtar of בית דין beis
din is, as we remember yesterday, that an admission before a בית
דין beis din doesn't need authorization. Okay, so if this really was
a שטר shtar of בית דין, beis din, then they could go
ahead and write the שטר shtar of this admission without being authorized.
So there was all of these indications that it was a בית
דין beis din שטר shtar by the way of the language in
which it was used. ולא הוה כתב ביה במותב תלתא הוינא וחד
ליתוהי, V'lo hava kasav bayeh b'mosav tlata havina v'chad leiseih, there's a
one little problem: there's only two signatures at the bottom and a
בית דין beis din is supposed to be three. Mind you could
have something occur before a בית דין Beis Din and then one
person died. But then what you would write in the שטר Shtar
would be, we were a convocation of three, one person is no
longer with us, and therefore and here's what happened and then signed
it, but that wasn't there. So you have these contradictory indications in
the שטר. Shtar. The language was a בית דין Beis Din language,
but there was only two signatures without an indication that it had
been that there had been three. Okay, three people there. So is
it a בית דין Beis Din שטר Shtar and then the admission
is good in front of them? Is it an עדים Eidim שטר
Shtar and then without authorization the admission is no good? So what
are you going to do? So סבר רבינא למימר, Savar Ravina l'meimar,
Ravina thought to say, היינו דרבי שמעון בן לקיש, hainu d'Reish Lakish,
let's apply Reish Lakish's principle that we assume the שטר Shtar was
done properly. So here too we'll assume that it was done with
a בית דין Beis Din and that one person, you know, wasn't
around to sign it or had passed away and they forgot to
mention that. But basically it was a בית דין Beis Din שטר.
Shtar. And it was a proper שטר. Shtar. אמר ליה רב נתן
בר אמי, Amar lei Rav Natan bar Ami,
הכי אמרינן משמיה דרבא, hachi amrinan mishmei d'Rava, no, here's what we
say in the name of Rava, כל כי האי גוונא חיישינן לבית
דין טועה. kol ki hai gavna chaishinan l'Beis Din to'eh. No, no,
here we're afraid that it was a בית דין Beis Din in
error and that actually it was really only two people and it
wasn't really a בית דין. Beis Din. Now how's that different than
Reish Lakish? The reason it's different is obvious. Reish Lakish, everything in
the שטר Shtar looks right. Two witnesses testified to something. You don't
know a particular, right, you don't know if a particular adult or
not, but there's no indication in the שטר Shtar that he wasn't
an adult. So of course you can assume it was done right.
Even in the case right before this, right, they say that they're
writing a שטר, Shtar, it was all done right. They don't say
explicitly that they were authorized, but the very fact that they were
writing the שטר Shtar might be seen as evidence that they were
authorized. Here, however, the evidence shows that there were two people, not
three! So it could be that there were עדים Eidim who used
the language of בית דין. Beis Din. It could be two people
who thought that they were a בית דין Beis Din but they're
really not a בית דין Beis Din because there's only two. Okay?
So it's not just like, you know, so here it really seems
like it's there's something that's saying that it's not a כשר kasher
שטר, Shtar, that it's not it seems to be saying it's a
בית דין Beis Din and it's not a בית דין. Beis Din.
All right? So that we have to assume they made a mistake
and therefore you can assume that it was only either only a
בית דין Beis Din of two or it's two people and it
wasn't a בית דין Beis Din and they lacked the proper authorization.
So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אי
כתיב בי דינא, ei kasiv bei dina, תו לא צריך. tu lo
tzarich. If it's written in it, we, the בית דין, Beis Din,
you know, sort of heard this person admit in front of us,
then even if there's only two signatures, then you could apply Reish
Lakish. Then they're clearly recognizing that they're a בית דין, Beis Din,
it wasn't עדים, Eidim, and presumably everybody knows that a בית דין
Beis Din has three, so for some reason the third guy didn't
sign on.
Wait, but what about the opinion that two can be enough?
Okay, well, we're going to get to that too. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, ודילמא בי דינא חצוף הוא, v'dilma bei
dina chatzuf hu,
one minute, maybe it was only two, but they still wrote בית
דין Beis Din because sometimes you can have a בית דין Beis
Din of two, a like a בית דין חצוף, Beis Din chatzuf,
but it's still valid. דאמר שמואל שנים שדנו דיניהם דין אלא שנקראו
בית דין חצוף. d'amar Shmuel shnayim she'danu dineihem din ela she'nikrau Beis
Din chatzuf. If two people judge, its judged, it's just that they're
called an impudent בית דין. Beis Din. But nevertheless, so maybe they
were two? Now so what? If you're ruling like שמואל Shmuel that
two is good for a בית דין, Beis Din, so fine, then
they were a good בית דין. Beis Din. But the problem would
be that if you remember what we just said the other day
was that if you admit in front of two, it's not you
can't write a שטר Shtar unless you've been authorized. You need to
admit before three for a שטר Shtar to be written without authorization.
So even if in general we rule like שמואל Shmuel that two
could be a בית דין, Beis Din, two would not suffice for
writing a שטר Shtar without authorization. So the concern is is that
they were two, they considered themselves to be a בית דין, Beis
Din, they wrote the language of a בית דין, Beis Din, but
they weren't authorized to write a שטר Shtar because they weren't three.
So how do you know that this is valid? So the גמרא
Gemara says, דכתיב ביה, d'kasiv bei, no, it's written in it is
בי דינא דרב אשי, Bei Dina d'Rav Ashi, the בית דין Beis
Din of Rav Ashi. Okay? So the בית דין Beis Din of
Rav Ashi presumably we mean we were a serious בית דין Beis
Din and therefore clearly there were three of us. So the גמרא
Gemara says ודילמא רבנן דבי רב אשי כשמואל סבירא להו, v'dilma rabanan
d'bei Rav Ashi k'Shmuel sevira lehu, okay, but maybe they hold that
two is good? Of course, you know, would they call themselves a
בית דין Beis Din of Rav Ashi where they do something that
would be considered חצוף? chatzuf? But anyway, דכתיב ביה, d'kasiv bei, so
fine, it was written in it was ואמרנו ליה לרבנן דבי רב
אשי v'amarno lei l'rabanan d'bei Rav Ashi or ואמר לן רב אשי,
v'amar lan Rav Ashi, Rav
Ashi sort of instructed us to serve as a בית דין Beis
Din and to write this שטר. Shtar. So under those circumstances you
don't assume they did something that was חצוף chatzuf as it were
and that they did everything properly and therefore there's basically almost explicit
indication that they were a real full בית דין Beis Din of
three and then they just forgot to have the third guy sign
on. Okay. But that's the end of that, that you need to
have two to authorize two to write a שטר Shtar for an
admission or it be in front of three and then even without
authorization. What do you do if it's not clear if the two
were authorized or if the three were a בית דין Beis Din
or if there were really three? That was this discussion. Can you
assume from the presence of a שטר Shtar that it was valid?
Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אמר להן אחד אני ראיתי את אביכם
שהטמין מעות בשידה תיבה ומגדל ואמר של פלוני הם של מעשר שני
הם. Amar lahen echad ani raisi es avichem she'hitmin maos b'shida teiva
u'migdal v'amar shel ploni hem shel maaser sheni hem. So remember, the
context here is when is an admission binding? Okay? So now normally
it's like, I... Bringing two witnesses that Gloria admitted to me that
she owes me a hundred dollars. So I'm trying to get that
money from Gloria and Gloria's trying to get out of it. Okay.
Here is a question where maybe the person isn't trying to get
out of it. He's trying to do the right thing, but only
if he's really obligated. Okay, so what happens? So I come and
I say to Gloria, Gloria, I saw your father hide money in
a box, okay, and he told me that that money really was
belonged to Joe. פלוני הן שמעשר שני הן, Ploni hen she-ma'aser sheni
hen, or it was מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. Okay, does Gloria
have a responsibility to believe me? You got it, Gloria wants to
do the right thing, but she doesn't want to flush money down
the toilet. She doesn't want to give money away that she doesn't
have to, right? So does she have a responsibility to believe me
in that case? Okay, and I'm only one person, okay, I'm not
two people, whatever.
The guy that saw, I came and I saw Gloria, I saw
your father hide this money and said it belonged to Joe. Okay,
it's not in front of a בית דין, Beit Din, I'm not
two witnesses. Okay, so and maybe even if I'm telling the truth,
maybe the father was doing it for some other reason.
We had variations of it, but what do you mean? But this
is a case where nobody is demanding money from Gloria. Gloria wants
to do the right thing.
It's sort of like בפינו הודה, Befino hoda, you know, like meaning
he admitted that I owe this guy money. It's the same thing.
I'm thinking that this is so-and-so's money, it's like saying I owe
so-and-so money.
No, first of all, he didn't do an admission. He was just
talking or whatever. No, it's very different. First of all, he didn't
admit to the other person. We said the other day that the
other person had to be— they had to admit to the other
person that they're liable, before that was there. Right, and the thing
is so קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. Okay, but the difference is is
that is that it's not like Joe's trying to force the money
from Gloria. He wouldn't be allowed to in that case. Gloria just
wants to do the right thing. Okay, so should she believe me
or not? Okay, so let's let's go. Okay, we're going to get
to that. Okay.
לא אמר כלום. Lo amar klum. Now if— I'm sorry, בבית, be-bayit,
if I say that the money is hidden in the house, then
לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, then you don't have to believe
me. Okay, maybe I'm totally making it up, who knows what? Okay,
and it's not— the admission isn't meaningful. בשדה, be-sadeh, let's say I
said the money is hidden under that, you know, rock there in
the field, so דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, then it's good. You know
why? Because I could go when nobody's around to the field and
take that money myself. And if Gloria goes and she uncovers the
rock and she sees the money whatever, so heck, if I could
have taken the money myself, it's like a מיגו, migo, I must
be telling the truth. Why would I be making that up? כללו
של דבר, Klalo shel davar,
the general principle is, כל שבידו ליטול דבריו קיימין אין בידו ליטול
לא אמר כלום. Kol she-beyado litol devarav kayamin, ein beyado litol lo
amar klum. Without that, it doesn't mean anything for a couple of
reasons. Number one, I'm only one witness, I'm not two witnesses. Okay,
and number two, like, you know, it wasn't an admission in front
of the other person. Maybe there were, you know, who knows what?
Okay, but here it's only question is that Gloria wants to know
should she believe me if she wants to do the right thing.
הרי שראו את אביהם שהטמין מעות בשידה תיבה ומגדל. Harei she-ra'u et
avihem she-itmin ma'ot be-shida teivo u-migdal.
Now, let's say somebody— they saw, they themselves saw their father hide
this money. ואמר שפלוני הן שמעשר שני הן. Ve-amar she-ploni hen she-ma'aser
sheni hen. In the exact same case, if they themselves saw their
father, that's almost like a, you know, it should be obvious what
they have to do. But no, even here we'll see why this
was questionable because, again, it was not like he was admitting to
the person he was obligated. אם כמספר דבריו קיימין. Im kimsaper devarav
kayamin. If he's basically telling whoever he's telling this to that he
wants them to know because he wants to make sure the right
thing gets done with it. Okay, then obviously that's binding. You heard
the person himself say what the nature of that money was. אם
כמערים, Im kema'arim, if
however it's clear that he's that he's being a little, you know,
like scheming— I mean, that's not a good word here, but whatever.
You know, there's something else going on. Like maybe he's putting his
money away and he doesn't want his kids to take the money
and to go spend it on ice cream or something. So he
tells them it's someone else's money. But, you know, there's indications that
he's making up a story in order to get people's hands, you
know, his family's hands off of it. So in that case לא
אמר כלום, lo amar klum, it's not binding. הרי שהיה מצטער על
מעות שהניח לו אביו. Harei she-haya mitzta'er al ma'ot she-hini'ach lo aviv.
Now, let's say, so somebody was worried, like he— you know, he
knew that his father had left, you know, had passed away and
left money, he knew thousands of dollars, he knew his father had
been hoarding, but he couldn't find where it was. ובא בעל החלום,
U-va ba'al ha-chalom, and in a dream somebody appeared to him, the
literally the owner of the dreams, whoever it is whoever it does
who creates dreams, came— the Sandman, thank you, came to him and
אמר לו amar lo said, כך וכך הן, Kach ve-kach hen,
I'll tell you, there were two thousand three hundred
and forty eight dollars, במקום פלוני הן, be-makom ploni hen, and you'll
find them under the third rock, you know, in the backyard, okay,
but you should know שמעשר שני הן. she-ma'aser sheni hen. It was
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. Okay, and then the person got up
in the morning and they looked under the third rock and they
found two thousand three hundred and forty eight dollars. So so everything
was, you know, verified. You also have to believe that it's מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni money. So the גמרא Gemara says, זה היה מעשה,
Ze haya ma'aseh, this happened, ואמרו דברי חלומות לא מעלין ולא מורידין.
ve-amru divrei chalomot lo ma'alin ve-lo moridin. Yeah, you don't have to
put any stock in dreams. So it's all very nice that it
was exactly... that amount of money and there was exactly where you
said, but you don't have to worry that actually this is some
direct message from God or from the
afterworld, and maybe it was a coincidence, maybe it was your own
subconscious somehow that you were aware and you weren't aware that it
was there, although I don't understand why your subconscious also thought it
was מעשר שני Maaser Sheini money, but somehow you're allowed to selectively
believe the dream. Okay, there's no evidence, which is a great story.
Yes, Michael.
So what I'm understanding is that this, you know, again we have
this whole thing that maybe he's מודה, modeh, he doesn't want to
seem like you know, מודה, modeh, like dead—you know, he's doing it
because he doesn't want to appear wealthy, right? Right. Here it's not
brought in, so what happened to that? So are we saying that
all the time about not being
wealthy—because not being wealthy is when other people are—no, that was when
like, that was like when there were other people involved. This was
just totally like within the family.
What happened to the witness, right?
Yeah, if I'm admitting to you to outside people and then you
want to whatever, maybe I want the outside world to have certain
perceptions of me. This is all like internal within the family, so
there's none of this שלא להוציא לעז. shelo le-hotzi laaz. There's other
factors. I'm doing it so my kids don't get to the money
and use it for themselves, I'm doing it whatever. Okay, this is
like completely different. I can't get detailed, I already identified some of
the key points, but there's obvious ways in which this is different.
The frame is not one of admitting to a בית דין, Beit
Din, it's somebody doing something on his own and sharing with somebody
else what they're doing. Okay, there's like, you know, we're dealing here
with like an עד אחד, eid echad, we're not dealing with an
admission, it's internal within the family, so there's a whole different sort
of set of considerations.
So do you mean the עד אחד eid echad is internal within
the family?
I don't know, but it's not the same. It's not the—it seems
like it's all very much like a more of a private affair.
Okay, שנים אומרים זכאי. Shenayim omrim zakai. Now,
moving up. Now we get—so we move beyond the issue of admission,
what type of admission is binding, and we go to the whole
issue of the deliberation. Two say innocent, one say guilty, you know,
then whatever, then it's innocent. Two say guilty, one say innocent, guilty.
And then it says at the end, and you're not allowed to
go ahead and the one who voted in the minority vote can't
go to the other guy and say, you know, I really wanted
to vote for you, but you know, what could I do, they
outweighed me, etc., and they call the person a הולך רכיל, holech
rachil, like a talebearer and so on. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. מיכתב היכי כתבי? Michtav heichi katvi?
Now, when you write out the judgment of the court, the court
decision, what do you write when it's a two-to-one decision? Okay, so
רבי יוחנן אמר זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan amar Zakai, you write, we have
all found that the person is innocent, or we the court find
the person innocent. ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says no, you write down the minority opinion. פלוני ופלוני מזכין
ופלוני מחייב. Ploni u-ploni mezakin u-ploni mechayev.
You know, judge one and two said that he's innocent, and judge
three said he's guilty. You actually record the minority opinion. Now how
does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish fit with the משנה? Mishnah? The משנה
Mishnah says you're not supposed to go to the other guy and
say, hey, I wanted to find in your favor. So the גמרא
Gemara never explicitly explores that, but it seems—and this could be a
reading of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, there's a question in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
where it's talking about רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish,
but it seems that the obvious way of making a distinction is
that it's one thing to say I'm allowed to say that I
disagreed, that I was in the minority opinion. What I can't do
is I can't go and I can't sow dissent. I can't say
to Michael, Michael, I really disagreed with them, I really—I thought their
reason was so bad, I was siding with you, I was really
arguing your case, but they outweighed me. That's like undermining the weight
of their authority and decision and it's sowing dissent and it's picking
sides, right? We can all—if I don't go to Michael and the
three of us say, we as a court came to the conclusion
that he's guilty, the following two ruled חייב chayav and this one
ruled innocent and our conclusion is that he's guilty. So we're allowed
to indicate our positions as long as we start to sort of
speak with the shared authority of the court and as opposed to
the way in which you go over to a side and you
sort of sow dissent. Okay, that seems to be, although that's not
explicit in the גמרא. Gemara. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish never explicitly says
how his position is different than—you know, accommodates the משנה. Mishnah. ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says you record the minority opinion. All right. רבי
אלעזר... Rabbi Elazar...
what?
Two people or... could ריש לקיש Reish Lakish be understood to mean
two of us said one thing and one of us said the
other?
Oh, I see. That's interesting. You mean if the whole court, rather
than I myself say, here I dissented and here's my dissenting opinion,
if the court as a whole speaks in the voices of all
three of us and say, the following two of us ruled חייב
chayav and this one of us ruled guilty—ruled innocent, then the whole
court is speaking as a unified whole, rather than a person separating
themselves out. Is that what you're saying?
Or even if the court says,
we decided two to one.
Right, without identifying. But no, here it does identify. It says פלוני
ופלוני מזכין ופלוני מחייב. Ploni u-ploni mezakin ve-ploni mechayev. But you're still
saying it's different if it's written out as, here's how we decided,
two of us said this, one of us said this, and that
also creates that sense of unified voice. Right. So I think that's
an excellent point. So I think something along that line allows ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish to have the minority opinion expressed or express himself,
but not be the undermining. mining that's that the משנה Mishnah doesn't
allow.
Okay so the next line is what you were suggesting, Rabbi.
רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar Omeir, not exactly. No.
רבי אלעזר אומר מדבריהן נזכה פלוני. Rabbi Elazar Omeir midevriehen nizaka ploni.
From our deliberations our conclusions was that so-and-so was found innocent. So
maybe it's a little because meaning the fact that you say from
our deliberations you could have just said we find him innocent, meaning
maybe that's a like a signal word that there was a debate
but our conclusion was the following. So it's unclear whether according to
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar would they write the same language when it
was unanimous, right? Maybe would they only write that language when it
was a debate or would they write it even unanimous? But even
if they only if they wrote it only when there was a
debate then you're right it's a little bit like גלוי. galui. The
difference is that it doesn't identify who says what and it still
speaks very much in a very unified voice as opposed to saying
it was two to one, it's not explicit, it's implicit, you know,
that there was some dis- that there was a debate. Okay so
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What would be a difference between them? איכא
בינייהו
לשלומי אינהו מנתא בהדייהו. ika beinaihu lishlumay ihu mantsa behadyhu. Let's say
the court was found to have ruled incorrectly and in some cases
which we'll get to in a later פרק perek and we've discussed
earlier also if the court ruled incorrectly the judgment stands and they
have to reimburse the other side. Okay so if that happens does
the person in the minority position who has now been proven correct,
does he have to also now reimburse the other side? Well why
should he ever? Well
because let's take a look. דלמאן דאמר זכאי משלם. deliman damar zakai
meshaleim. If the whole court in the end has all three of
them ruling, you know, I'm forced to rule with you guys but
at the end of the day that's the way the court works
and I am putting my voice together with yours and we're all
ruling innocent, then I'm part of the incorrect ruling and I would
have to go ahead and pay. Okay the גמרא Gemara is going
to retract this because it does not seem fair. Okay ולמאן דאמר
פלוני ופלוני מזכין ופלוני פלוני מחייבין לא משלם. uliman damar ploni uploni
mazakin u-ploni uploni mechayvin lo meshaleim. But if I'm allowed to maintain
my separate dissenting voice then I wouldn't have to pay if we
were all found to have ruled incorrectly. So גמרא Gemara says one
minute. ולמאן דאמר זכאי משלם? uliman damar zakai meshaleim? The one that
says that I have to sort of speak with a unified voice
and I have to say innocent, you're going to make me pay?
לימא להו. leima lehu. Why can't I say to these other two
judges אילו דידי צייתון, ilu didi tzaitan, had you listened to me,
okay this is a great I told you so, had you just
listened to me אתון נמי לא שלמתון, atun nami lo shalumtun, you
wouldn't have to be paying! It's clear I was right all along!
So because of the rules of the court that I was forced
to sign on with your judgment I'm going to have to pay?
That doesn't make any sense. אלא איכא בינייהו לשלומי אינהו מנתא דידיה.
ela ika beinaihu lishlumay ihu mantza didey. Here's the thing: I will
never have to pay. I was always in the right for that.
Do you two pay two-thirds of the judgment or do you pay
my third as well? All right. So למאן דאמר זכאי משלם. liman
damar zakai meshaleim. If we wrote as a unit we're all saying
innocent, so then we're all saying innocent, not that two-thirds of us
are saying innocent and one is saying guilty. We're all saying innocent,
but really it's you two speaking for all three of us. So
since it's you two speaking for all three of us and you're
saying innocent, then you're taking the full burden of that פסק psak
and therefore you're going to pay the full amount.
Okay ולמאן דאמר פלוני ופלוני מזכין ופלוני ופלוני מחייבין לא משלם. uliman
damar ploni uploni mazakin uploni uploni mechayvin lo meshaleim. But if in
the end our judgment is written with my dissenting opinion, okay, לא
משלם, lo meshaleim, then you're only taking two-thirds of the responsibility of
the פסק psak and you only pay two-thirds. All right. Let's just
keep on going because the גמרא Gemara is not going to stick
with it. ולמאן דאמר זכאי משלם? uliman damar zakai meshaleim? One minute.
Even if you're we just say a unified language of innocent, you
two are going to pay the full amount? לימרו ליה. leimru lei.
So why don't you two say to me אילו לאו אפי הדין,
ilu la apahadan, if you hadn't, you know, been part of our
group לא הוה סלקא דינא מידי. lo havya salka dina midi. We
wouldn't have had a פסק דין! psak din! The only reason it
was a פסק דין psak din was because you were part of
us. So even if you two were the only ones who ruled
innocent, you were not the only two that were part of the
process. So there is no way all three of us were part
of the process. So there's no way you should have to pay
the full amount. Okay that's I don't know that's, you know, you
two are fully responsible, you ruled that way. To me it makes
sense that the two of you pay the full amount but the
גמרא Gemara sort of says that in this type of a case
the party that was, you know, had the wrong judgment against him
and is now being compensated by the court only gets two-thirds compensated.
It's clearly not fair I would have to pay. But it's also
saying it's not fair that you have to pay because you didn't
do it all by yourself. Okay although it was all your vote
that led to that conclusion. Okay. So אלא איכא בינייהו ela ika
beinaihu fine said the גמרא, Gemara, it sounds like at the end
of the day you only pay two-thirds. What difference does it make
how we write it? איכא בינייהו משום לא תלך רכיל בעמיך. ika
beinaihu mishum lo teleich rachil be-amecha. Right? The question is how much,
I mean it's not really an איכא בינייהו ika beinaihu because there's
no practical implications. This is less what is the... What derives from
their debate, but more what's behind their debate. Right, so you understand
the first question was like, okay, they debate how you write it,
what would be the practical implication beyond the fact that you, how
you record it. Now we're saying, no, no, no, the only practical
implication is how you record it, but what's that debate about? So
what that debate is about is how much are you concerned that
the recording of the minority opinion is a type of a tale-bearing
and sowing of dissent? Rabbi Yochanan says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. אמר
זכאי משום לא תלך רכיל *Rabbi Yochanan amar zakai mishum lo telech
rachil*. We have to only say the unified voice, because anything else
would be like sowing dissent. Resh Lakish says ריש לקיש אמר פלוני
ופלוני מזכין ופלוני מחייב משום דמיחזי כשיקרא *Resh Lakish amar ploni u-ploni
mezakin u-ploni mechayiv mishum de-mechzi keshikra*. To not write the dissenting position
would be like a falsehood. It's not true. All three of us
did not say זכאי *zakai*. And besides the מיחזי כשיקרא *mechzi keshikra*,
you know, there's also the question about for the benefit of future
generations, like why we record a דעת יחיד *da'as yachid*. Right? You
know, we always record a דעת יחיד *da'as yachid* in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* because we want that opinion preserved for the sake of
future courts and future הלכה *halakha* deliberations. So you could say the
same thing here, although here it's not clear when you record the
dissenting opinion, you record the reason. There's no indication that you record
the reason. We'll get to that maybe later. Okay, but anyway, so
that's why the only thing that's emphasized here is not the, but
even in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, the משנה *Mishna* says a minority
opinion and it doesn't give the reason. So you know, there could
be a תורה *Torah* reason, like a תורה *Torah* knowledge reason to
want to maintain that. But anyway, all this mentions is the fact
of מיחזי כשיקרא *mechzi keshikra*. It's not true that all three of
them ruled the following way. How does it deal with the משנה
*Mishna* of לא תלך רכיל *lo telech rachil*? That's not explicit, but
as I said, first of all as Gloria said, it's not the
person maybe speaking in their own voice, it's the whole court identifying
what the vote was. And the person isn't going over and picking
sides and trying to side with, you know, the other party. It's
just a record of how we voted. Okay, so that's, well let's
finish it. That's what ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* says. Rabbi Elazar אית
ליה דמר ואית ליה דמר *islei de-mar ve-islei de-mar*. He's concerned about
a type of indicating a debate and לא תלך רכיל *lo telech
rachil* and revealing the private deliberation, but he's concerned about the מיחזי
כשיקרא *mechzi keshikra*. So therefore, so therefore what does he do? הילכך
כתבי הכי מדבריהם נזדכה פלוני *hilkacha katvi hachi midivreihem nizdaka ploni*. You
write it in a language, and this indicates maybe you would only
use this language when there was a debate, that signals that it
was not unanimous.
The vote concluded that so-and-so was guilty. The vote concluded that so-and-so
was innocent. It alludes to the fact that it's not, that it
wasn't unanimous and that there was a debate, but it doesn't give
the particulars, so it keeps what's private, it still keeps it private.
So that's a nice balance of those two types of things. Yes.
By the way, the idea of precedent that we have in our
case law here, like so we sometimes come across where it looks
like there's precedent in terms of a rabbi will say well so-and-so
ruled earlier in this way. Right. But how does it fit in
here, precedent, if we don't know, you know, there was only one...
Oh, how could, could you use a precedent
by a court?
Yeah, but you know, that's a good question. Look, הלכה *halakha* also
deals with the fact about, you know, there's a question about how
a particular rabbi ruled, but sometimes also the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks
about like what is the, you know, you know, what the general
like סוגיא *sugya* is, meaning like what's the general practice out there
of, you know? So if the courts are ruling in a certain
way, you know, it does establish that this is a practice of
at least one court, you know, even without knowing who the particular
רבנים *rabbonim* are or how the particular רבנים *rabbonim* voted. So it
still has some weight, it's a good question, it still has some
weight in setting precedent even without knowing the specific rabbi.
Would you say they do pass on what the debate was in
that particular case and what the ruling was? They just...
Oh, you mean how much do they indicate according to any of
these opinions, even ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*, what was it that we
were debating? Right, that's not clear. Meaning at the end of the
day, could be we all agreed on the הלכה *halakha* and we
were debating the facts, or we all agreed on the facts and
we were debating the הלכה *halakha*, or you know, or it could
have been of a million different legal points we were debating, and
none of that is, there's no indication that any of that is
recorded. Right. So this is much more about practical applied law, you
know, whereas you're right, like, like if you think about it in
our court system, the way I mean, again, Gloria,
feel free to jump in and correct me, but the way like,
it's true that like in the universities or whatever, legal scholars write
briefs or opinions, but the way certain legal ideas really become part
of the discourse is because they get recorded in court opinions on
actual cases, whereas here you get the sense that the ideas that
are part of the discourse, it's what's debated in the university, you
know, in the בית מדרש *beis medrash*, those become the relevant ideas
and the actual practical court decisions, you don't get the, there's no
detail, you just get the bottom line. You don't know what the
deliberations are. So it sounds like it's a different type of a
model, which could be because, as we learned earlier, you know, there's
a whole range of people that are acceptable to be דיינים *dayanim*.
You don't always have the biggest תלמידי חכמים Chachamim *talmidei chachamim*. being
the דיינים, so it does seem here that the debates of the
actual court that's פוסקנינג paskening are not as relevant to the legal
discourse, like the flip of my sense of what we have in
America, in America.
There's also a difference between findings of fact and findings of law.
With findings of fact, you can't even appeal it.
It's the judges
who are hearing that, that's it. Only findings of law that's appealable.
Right, right. So here, you don't know, was it debated about? Right,
what was the issue? Was it fact, was it law, exactly. Right,
but it is, but certainly what you're not seeing, and we'll get
to it in later, or תוספות Tosafos will raise this issue, how
much and under what circumstances would you ever record what actually were
the issues that were at debate. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. גמר את הדבר היו מכניסים. Gamar et hadavar hayu machnisim. Once
they were finished, they would bring the people in and they'd give
their ruling, they'd finish their deliberations. למאן, Leman, who would you bring
in? Who was standing outside of the court? So אילימא לבעלי דינים,
Eileima l'baalei dinim, you had the litigants outside of the court when
the judges were deliberating. So התם קיימי, Hatam kaimei, there's no indication
in the משנה that the litigants weren't there during the deliberations. Now
that's bizarre. You would assume, especially because this whole thing of הולך
רכיל, holech rachil, you would assume you don't want an audience for
your deliberations. Okay, so in the end we're going to actually say
that the litigants were not there. But for now we're assuming the
litigants were there and the witnesses were outside of the court. And
then at the end, the witnesses are brought back in, which is
bizarre. Who needs to bring the witnesses back in? So אלא לעדים.
Ela l'eidim. כמאן, K'man, who is this going like, that you would
need to bring the witnesses back in? דלא כרבי נתן. D'lo k'Rabbi
Natan. Not like רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. And we saw some, now
we're going to see things we've seen in the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. דתניא ואין עדות מצטרפת עד שיראו שניהם כאחד. De-tanya v'ein
eidut mitztarefet ad she-yiru shnehem k'echad. If people, the testimony of two
separate witnesses doesn't combine unless they saw the exact same thing at
the same event. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר אפילו בזה אחר זה.
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer afilu b'zeh achar zeh. Even sequentially, one
saw a loan and one saw an admission on the other day,
or one saw a loan on Monday and one saw a loan
on Tuesday, but at the end of the idea, they both testify
that this guy owes a hundred dollars, a different hundred dollars. That's
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha's position. We'll see more
of that. Okay, ואין עדות מתקיימת בבית דין עד שיעידו שניהם כאחד.
v'ein eidut mitkayemet b'veit din ad she-yadu shnehem k'echad. The thing we're
going to focus on is the second part.
They not only have to see it together, but they also have
to come and testify together. רבי נתן אומר שומעין דברו של זה
היום וכשיבוא חברו למחר שומעין דברו. Rabbi Natan omer shomin dvaro shel
zeh hayom u-chshe-yavo chaveiro l'machar shomin dvaro. No, you could accept one
witness one day and one witness the next day. So therefore, how
does, why is this relevant? So the גמרא Gemara's thinks, if it
means you bring the witnesses back in, why are you bringing the
witnesses back in? The only reason you would bring the witnesses back
in is after you individually accepted the witnesses' testimony, you want them
both in the court at the same time because we rule against
רבי נתן Rabbi Natan and say they have to both testify in
the court at the same time. I don't know, nobody sees that.
Don't worry, the גמרא Gemara going to reject it. So the גמרא
Gemara says, לא לעולם לבעלי דינים. Lo l'olam l'baalei dinim. No, we're
not talking about the witnesses. We're talking about the litigants. And the
litigants weren't there during the deliberations, and now when it comes time
for the פסק, psak, they're brought back in, which makes total sense.
רבי נחמיה היא, Rabbi Nechemia hi, it's רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. Okay,
where was I? רבי נחמיה היא. Rabbi Nechemia hi. דתניא רבי נחמיה
אומר כך היו מנהגם של נקי הדעת שבירושלים. De-tanya Rabbi Nechemia omer
kach hayu minhagam shel nekiyei hadaas she-bi-Yerushalayim. Here's the way that the
clean, whatever the, I don't even know how to translate that idiom.
But anyway, the refined people would do in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. This is
the best way to do the process of the court. מכניסים לבעלי
דינים, Machnisim l'baalei dinim, you bring in the
litigants, שומעין דבריהם, shomin divreihem, you hear their different positions, ומכניסים את
העדים שומעין דבריהם, u-machnisim et ha-eidim shomin divreihem, then you bring in
the witnesses,
ומוציאים אותם לחוץ, u-motzin otam l'chutz, then you put everybody outside, okay,
ונושאים ונותנים בדבר, v'nosin v'nosin b'davar, and you deliberate. גמר את הדבר
מכניסים, Gamar et hadavar machnisim, and then when you finish, then you
bring them all back in.
Wait, even the עדים eidim too, or just the בעלי דינים? baalei
dinim?
That's not clear. Let's take a look. Mostly the בעלי דינים. baalei
dinim. The עדים eidim we don't care about. Go home. Yeah, והתניא,
v'ha-tanya, but wait, we have a ברייתא baraita says גמר את הדבר
מכניסים את העדים, gamar et hadavar machnisim et ha-eidim, that it seems
like it was the עדים eidim that you're emphasizing bringing them back
in. And the only reason for that to be would be because
you want them to testify together. So the גמרא Gemara's says fine,
ההיא דלא כרבי נתן. hahi d'lo k'Rabbi Natan. That's not our משנה.
That would be not like רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, that would emphasize
the עדים eidim and you need to bring the עדים eidim after
you've gotten their testimony individually, you need to bring them in together
to get their testimony together.
Or maybe just more like see the impact of what you're doing?
Could be. I know, but that's not the way the גמרא Gemara
reading it. גופא. Gufa. Now let's look at this debate, this רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha and this רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan issue. לעולם אין עדות מצטרפת עד שיראו שניהם כאחד. L'olam ein
eidut mitztarefet ad she-yiru shnehem k'echad. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר אפילו
בזה אחר זה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer afilu b'zeh achar zeh.
Even sequentially. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflegi? What's the debate about? איבעית אימא
קרא איבעית אימא סברא. I-ba'it eima k'ra i-ba'it eima svara. If you
want, I'll tell you it's a פסוק, pasuk, and if you want,
I'll tell you it's a סברא. svara. איבעית אימא סברא, I-ba'it eima
svara, if you want I'll tell you it's a סברא. svara. Okay,
I guess I have to take a moment to pause here
to say, you know, that this phrase and similar phrases really
indicate the sort of radical nature of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba-al
peh, that we're Equally prepared to hear an argument based on סברא
sevara as we are based on a פסוק. pasuk. You know, sometimes
it says you go this way, you go that way, but after
it says if you want it's a פסוק, pasuk, if you want
it's a סברא, sevara, it starts with the סברא, sevara, which almost
could be read as giving a little primacy to the סברא. sevara.
Sometimes the גמרא Gemara is even more explicit. The גמרא Gemara says
למה לי קרא סברא
הוא. lama li kra sevara hu. Why do you need to prove
it to me from a פסוק, pasuk, I could figure it out
logically? Okay, so first we should just at least appreciate this phrase.
Alright, anyway, אי בעית אימא קרא ואי בעית אימא סברא. i ba'it
eima kra ve-i ba'it eima sevara. אי בעית אימא סברא, i ba'it
eima sevara, here's the סברא. sevara. אמנה קא מסהיד והאי לא קא
מסהיד אהאי. a-maneh ka masahid ve-hai lo ka masahid a-hai. So one
set of witnesses—one witness says I saw him borrow a hundred dollars
on Monday, and one says I saw him borrow a hundred dollars
on Wednesday. So they're talking about a different hundred dollars, so they
can't combine. That's the opinion that says they don't combine.
ואידך, ve-idach, and the other one will say,
אמנה בעלמא תרוייהו קא מסהדי. a-maneh be-alma tarvaihu ka masahadi. No, they're
both—I don't really care about the particulars, what I care is, does
he owe a hundred dollars or not? And they both admit that
the person is in debt a hundred dollars. So therefore they're saying—therefore
it combines. ואי בעית אימא קרא, ve-i ba'it eima kra, and if
you want I'll say it's based on a פסוק, pasuk, דכתיב, de-chtiv,
והוא עד או ראה או ידע. ve-hu ed o ra'ah o yada.
This is by an oath whether you don't know testimony, and it
says and in fact the person was a witness, he either saw
or he knows. דתניא, de-tanya, ממשמע שנאמר לא יקום עד אחד. mi-mashma
she-ne'emar lo yakum ed echad.
One witness can't go up against a person, I know עד ed
means one. מה תלמוד לומר אחד? ma talmud lomar echad? Why does
it have to say עד אחד, ed echad, one witness? זה בנין
אב, ze binyan av, to tell you this serves as a paradigm.
כל מקום שנאמר עד הרי כאן שנים. kol makom she-ne'emar ed harei
kan shenayim. The עד ed by itself would mean two, unless it
says אחד echad then it means one. עד שיפרוט לך הכתוב אחד.
ad she-yafrit lecha ha-katuv echad. Okay, now how's that relevant for us?
ואפקיה רחמנא בלשון חד. ve-afkeih rachamana be-lishon chad. So if עד ed
means two, and why—even if we accept that the word עד ed
means two, why does it refer to two people with a singular
noun? Why does it refer to two people with the one word
עד? ed? Means that they're fully unified. Okay, they're fully unified, they're
testifying to the same thing. למימרא דעד דחזו תרוייהו כחד. le-meimra de-ad
de-chazu tarvaihu ke-chad. They have to see exactly the same thing. They
have to—and actually, let me—let me even translate it more precisely. They
have to see as one. The two of them are functioning as
one person. So they witness it as one person and therefore they
both have to have witnessed the same event. Okay, that's the position
of the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. ואידך והוא עד או ראה או
ידע, ve-idach ve-hu ed o ra'ah o yada, מכל מקום. mi-kol makom.
No, או ראה או ידע o ra'ah o yada is a way
of saying however you know, even if you know in different ways,
you know, you don't have to—you know, any of those it always—it
all's good for being an עד. ed. Okay, so that's that debate.
Now, how about the debate of whether they have to testify together
or not? ואין עדותן מתקיימת בבית דין עד שיעידו שניהם כאחד ורבי
נתן אומר שומעין דבריו של זה היום וכשיבא חבירו למחר שומעין דבריו.
ve-ein edutan mitkayemet be-veit din ad she-ya'idu sheneihem ke-echad ve-rabbi natan omer
shome'in devarav shel ze ha-yom u-che-she-yavo chaveiro le-machar shome'in devarav. במאי קמיפלגי?
be-mai kamiflagi? What's the debate about? אי בעית אימא סברא ואי בעית
אימא קרא. i ba'it eima sevara ve-i ba'it eima kra. אי בעית
אימא סברא, i ba'it eima sevara, if you want it's a logical—it's
a base—it's a debate on a certain, you know, logical position. מר
סבר עד אחד כי אתי לשבועה אתי ולממונא לא אתי. mar savar
ed echad ki ata li-shvu'ah ata u-le-mamona lo ata.
If they come separately, then if one person presents himself and there's
not the other guy there in the wings, right, he just presented
himself and today on Monday when he comes to court you have
no idea there's another witness. So in that case, he is not
a witness to testify that would be seen as demanding that ראובן
Reuven pay שמעון. Shimon. His testimony as the single witness is demanding
that ראובן Reuven makes an oath to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so the
type of עד ed he is, he's an עד ed for a
שבועה, shvu'ah, that's what one עד ed does. Not an עד ed
to extract money. So therefore you—if you use him that way on
Monday, you can't change his role on Tuesday when the other עד
ed shows up.
ואידך, ve-idach, and the other one will say back, ואידך אטו כי
אתו בהדי הדדי בחד פומא קא מסהדי? ve-idach atu ki atu bahadi
hadadi be-chad puma ka masahadi? I don't understand. And let's say ראובן
Reuven and שמעון—the Shimon two עדים edim both come on Monday. They're
not talking in—with one mouth. First one testifies and then the other
testifies. So why don't we say when the first עד, ed, the
words come out of his mouth, they're only שבועה shvu'ah words? They're
not money words, okay? But we don't say that. We say that
what will happen afterwards will create the context of the testimony of
the first עד. ed. אלא מצטרפין להו. ela mitstarfin lehu. When the
other—after the other עד ed testifies, you combine them and you say
they're money עדים, edim, they're not שבועה shvu'ah עדים. edim. הכא נמי
ליצטרפו. hacha nami litsatrefu. Here too even if they come on different
days. So that's the סברא sevara debate. אי בעית אימא קרא, i
ba'it eima kra, or if it's a פסוק: pasuk: אם לא יגיד
ונשא עונו. im lo yagid ve-nasa avono. If he does not give
his testimony he will bear the burden of his sin, if he
swore falsely. ודכולי עלמא כרבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יהושע בן קרחה. ve-duchulei
alma ke-rabbanan de-paligi aleih de-rabbi yehoshua ben korcha. Now how's that debated
based on the פסוק? pasuk? Because what we have to know is
everybody
else—כרבנן—the ke-rabbanan Rabbis who argue on רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha, who say that they have to see it together. They
have to—the question is, okay, they have to see it together, but
do they have to testify
together? והכא בהקישא גופיה קמיפלגי. ve-hacha be-hekesha gufeih kamiflagi. The debate is,
do we link the giving of the testimony to the seeing of
the testimony? מר סבר Mar savar מקישנן, makishnan, או ראה או אם
לא יגיד, o ra'ah o im lo yagid, right? If he doesn't
tell. Right, it says first או ראה, o ra'ah, he saw, ואם
לא יגיד, ve-im lo yagid, and if he doesn't tell. So it
starts by talking about him seeing and then about him telling. So
the telling has to be like the seeing. The same way the
seeing, they see as one, when they tell they have to tell
as one. Okay, so מר סבר מקישנן הגדה לראיה, Mar savar makeeshnan
hagada lire'iyah, ומר סבר לא מקישנן. umar savar lo makeeshnan. No, the
seeing and the telling are different events, they have to see as
one but they don't have to tell as one. Now we have
a story and we saw this story in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it's
a little different in the בבלי. Bavli. רב שמעון בן אליקים הוי
משתקד עליה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא למסמכיה ולא קמסתייע מילתא. Rav Shimon
ben Elyakim havei mishtaked alei de-Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina lemismachye velo kamistaya
milta. Okay,
so רב שמעון בן אליקים Rav Shimon ben Elyakim was trying to
get רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose to give him סמיכה, smicha, but he
wasn't succeeding. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was whatever, was somehow getting out
of it, was somehow pushing him off. Yes,
יומא חד yoma chad what? You need somebody? I don't know what
to do if anybody wants to go, you're welcome to go. Anybody?
Joe? You want to go help out at the מנין minyan downstairs
Joe? Okay. יומא חד הוה יתיב קמיה דרבי יוחנן. Yoma chad hava
yasiv kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan. So one day they were sitting in front
of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan אמר להו amar lehu and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said to them, מי איכא דידע הלכה רבי יהושע בן
קרחה או לאו? mi ika deyada halacha Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha olav?
Does anybody know if we rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha that they have to, whether they have to see
it at the same time or not? Okay.
אמר ליה רב שמעון בן אליקים, amar lei Rav Shimon ben Elyakim,
I'm sorry, I misread the גמרא Gemara before because I think I
was getting it flipped because of the בבלי Bavli of the ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. I think the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, I'll double check, I think the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi had the different players who were getting סמיכה. smicha. But
this was רבי יהושע בן אליקים Rabbi Yehoshua ben Elyakim was trying
to get רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, was trying to give
סמיכה smicha to
רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא. Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose berabbi
Chanina was the one who they wanted to get סמיכה. smicha. Yes,
Michael? Okay, fine. Anyway, no, but that's what it seems. Okay, I
think the ירושלמי Yerushalmi had it that רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha that רב שמעון בן אליקים Rav Shimon ben Elyakim
was the one who needed סמיכה, smicha, but anyway, here it's רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina who wanted סמיכה. smicha. So
anyway, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. said, and in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it
was רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, here it's רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, does anybody know whether we rule like רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha or not? So אמר ליה
רב שמעון בן אליקים, amar lei Rav Shimon ben Elyakim, so רב
שמעון בן אליקים Rav Shimon ben Elyakim said דין ידע. dein yada.
Oh, this one knows. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina,
he knows whether how we פסקינן. paskinan. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
לימא איזו, leima eizo, let him say, let him say, how do
we פסקינן paskinan if he knows? So אמר ליה, amar lei, so
רב שמעון בן אליקים Rav Shimon ben Elyakim said לסמכיה מר ברישא.
lismachye Mar beresha.
If you want him to be part of the deliberations, you gotta
give him סמיכה smicha and then he'll tell you how we rule.
So סמכיה, samchye, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. now gave רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina סמיכה. smicha. I guess before he
was just יוסי ברבי חנינא, Yose berabbi Chanina, now he became רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina. He gave him סמיכה. smicha.
אמר ליה בני אמור לי כיצד שמעת. amar lei beni emor li
keitzad shamata. Okay, now you're part of our group, tell us how
did you hear? How do we פסקינן? paskinan? Do we פסקינן paskinan
like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha or not? אמר
ליה amar lei כך שמעתי שמודין רבי יהושע בן קרחה לרבי נתן.
kach shamati shemodin Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha le-Rabbi Natan. This is what
I heard: שמודין רבי יהושע בן קרחה לרבי נתן. shemodin Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha le-Rabbi Natan. רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
who says that they can see it separate,
he would agree to רבי נתן Rabbi Natan that they can report
it separate. If you can see it separate, you can certainly report
it separate. Now that doesn't tell you how we פסקינן, paskinan, right?
So אמר לזה הוצרכתי? amar lezeh hutzrachti? This I need you for?
השטא ומה עיקר ראיה בחדא דאמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה לא בעינן
הגדה מיבעיא? hashta uma ikar re'iyah behada de-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
lo bainan hagada mibaia? When it comes to actually seeing it, רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says you don't need to
see it together, הגדה מיבעיא? hagada mibaia? Is it is there any
question that according to him you wouldn't have to report it together?
אמר ליה amar lei הואיל ועלית לא תרד. ho'il ve-alita lo tered.
Fine, but since you already got סמיכה, smicha, I'm not going to
take your סמיכה smicha away from you.
Okay, so actually, so רב שמעון בן אליקים Rav Shimon ben Elyakim
succeeded in his attempt to get this guy סמיכה. smicha. אמר רבי
זירא שמע מינה, amar Rabbi Zeira sham mina, you hear from this,
גברא רבה כיון דאיסמך סמך. gavra raba kivan de-isamech samech. If a
great person gets סמיכה, smicha, the סמיכה smicha sticks, even if somehow
maybe there was some reason he wasn't, they didn't intend to exactly
give him סמיכה smicha at that time.
Okay, so ירושלמי Yerushalmi had it סמך סמך, samech samech, the guy
who is giving...
I know, but that doesn't seem, I think רש״י Rashi also doesn't
say, is there a רש״י Rashi here? Yeah, maybe you're right. Yeah,
but the גרסא girsa we have of סמך סמך samech samech is
a great person meaning רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan, If he gave סמיכה,
smicha, the סמיכה smicha sticks. But it seems like we're talking about...
he had to get סמיכה smicha in order to say what he
heard.
He did it! It was all a ruse! If you want in,
look, I've been trying to get this guy סמיכה smicha for as
long as time, you've been pushing him off. Now you realize he
needs him, if you give him the סמיכה smicha that he deserves
first, like you know, he was using it as leverage. It wasn't
necessary. Okay, but anyway, it's a little interesting little story, but just
I just want to check, first of all, I know in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi it was רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan and it wasn't רבי
Rabbi and it wasn't רבי יוחנן, but I also think that it
was what do you call it?
Let me see if I can quickly find it.
Also, also the other thing in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was it made
more sense because in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi the question wasn't do we
rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, it was
like do we rule like רבי נתן, Rabbi Nosson, and then at
least what he had to report was a little bit more relevant.
He said רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha would side
with רבי נתן. Rabbi Nosson. And even then he said big deal,
that was obvious anyway. But at least it was a little bit
more relevant, okay.
Let me just take a look.
Oh yeah. Here it says רבי יונתן הוה יתיב. Rabbi Yonatan hava
yatev.
Yeah, in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, listen to the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. אמר ליה
רבי יוסי בר אבא חנינא, Amar lei Rabbi Yossi bar Abba Chanina,
is that who we have here? רבי יוסי בר אבא חנינא Rabbi
Yossi bar Abba Chanina said, הא רבי שמעון בן יקים. Ha Rabbi
Shimon ben Yakim. So there was רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi
bar Chanina wanted to give סמיכה semicha to רבי שמעון בן אליקים.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elyakim. So and here, it seems like it's reverse,
it is the reverse. רבי שמעון בן אליקים Rabbi Shimon ben Elyakim
wanted to give סמיכה semicha to רבי יוסי בר אבא חנינא. Rabbi
Yossi bar Abba Chanina. So it's fascinating like so many of the
particulars are reversed between the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi in
this case. Okay, let's continue. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, said רב זירא, Rav Zeira,
שמע מינה גברא, Shma mina gavra, oh I just did that. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב הלכה רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abin amar Rav halacha Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. We
rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, that they
can testify on different days. בין בקרקע בין במטלטלין, Bein bekarka bein
bemetaltelin, whether קרקע karka or מטלטלין. metaltelin.
Why should it matter? We've already seen this in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
because maybe there's more reason to rule like him by קרקע. karka.
Because by money if I said Michael borrowed one hundred dollars on
Monday and another witness said he borrowed it on Wednesday, it's not
the same hundred dollars. But if one witness says Michael owns this
קרקע, karka, I saw him do a קנין kinyan whatever, and the
other one says here's how I know he owns this קרקע, karka,
they're both saying he owns the same plot of land. So that's
a better reason to rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha. But he says we rule like him in both cases.
עולא אמר הלכה רבי יהושע בן קרחה בקרקע, Ulla amar halacha Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha bekarka, we rule like him by קרקע, karka, אבל
לא במטלטלין, aval lo bemetaltelin, not by chattel. אמר ליה אביי הלכה
מכלל דפליגי? Amar lei Abaye halacha miklal de-pleigi? If you have to
rule like him by קרקע, karka, it sounds like they debate קרקע.
karka. ואמר רבי
אבא
אמר רב
הונא אמר
רב מודים חכמים לרבי יהושע בן קרחה בעדות
קרקע.
V'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav
Huna
amar Rav modim chachamim le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha be-edut karka.
אביי, Abaye, we have a position that says that when it comes
to land exactly for this reason because they're testifying on the same
plot of land, even the חכמים Chachamim would concede that you can
combine testimonies. דתניא רבי אידי בר אבין בנזיקין דבי קרנא. De-tanya Rabbi
Idi bar Abin bi-neziqin d'bei Karna. And he taught in the ברייתא
braita of מסכת נזיקין Masechet Nezikin in the ישיבה Yeshiva of קרנא,
Karna, מודים חכמים לרבי יהושע בן קרחה בעדות
קרן.
modim chachamim le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
be-edut keren. I know, yeah, that's
true. Anyway, בעדות בכור, be-edut bechor, when it comes to בכור, bechor,
so רש"י Rashi says it's whether an animal is a firstborn animal
and a כהן Kohen can he be trusted to say that it
has a מום mum in it or not a מום mum in
it and how did it get the מום. mum. Anyway, תוספות Tosafos
says it means whether a certain person is a man's firstborn son
to get a double portion. So if there's different testimonies and they
two witnesses know but from different points of view, can they combine?
So it's the same kid, whether he's a בכור bechor or not.
Like the same plot of land. ובעדות קרקע ובעדות חזקה. U-ve-edut karka
u-ve-edut chazaka. Now חזקה chazaka is a way of knowing the person
has קרקע. karka. Anyway, וכן שבבן ושבבת. ve-chen she-be-ven ve-she-be-bat. And similarly
by daughters and sons. What that means we'll get to in a
minute. But anyway, but the point is, we have אמוראים Amora'im who
say that when it comes to land, the חכמים agree to רבי
יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, it's not even debated. So
גמרא Gemara says, גברא אגברא קא רמית? gavra a-gavra ka ramis? So
how so what, okay, you're saying one position against another, they're different
rabbis. מר סבר פליגי, Mar savar pleigi, one is of the position
that they argue when it comes to the issue of עדות קרקע,
edut karka, ומר סבר לא פליגי, u-mar savar lo pleigi, that when
it comes to the issue of קרקע karka everybody agrees. Okay. מאי
וכן שבבן ושבבת? Mai ve-chen she-be-ven she-be-bat? Now what's the issue of
daughters and sons? And this again we saw in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
is very complicated in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, a little less complicated in
the בבלי, Bavli, I think. Anyway, אי לימא, ee-leima, so it means
testifying whether a young boy or girl is an adult. Do they
have the pube hair? Okay. אי לימא אחד אומר אחת בגביו ואחד
אומר אחת בכרסיו. Ee-leima echad omer achat be-gabav ve-echad omer achat be-keresav.
One says that I saw hair on the back, and one says
I saw it in the front. Okay, because there's hair in different
places of the body can count as the right hairs to indicate
that somebody's an adult. So if they were both in the same
place, then it would be good. But one says I saw it
in the front and one says I saw it in the back.
So the גמרא Gemara says, האי חצי דבר וחצי עדות הוא. Hai
chatzi davar ve-chatzi edut hu. That's not just half a you know,
an עד ed says one half an עד ed says the other.
Because here, one עד ed is saying I saw one pubic hair.
Well one pubic hair means that you saw that they're a קטן.
katan. And the other side, I saw one pubic hair. That means
you said it's a קטן. katan. So it's not just that your
two עדויות eduyot are separate, it's חצי עדות. chatzi edut. What you're
testifying on is the wrong thing. It's not like you're saying I
saw Michael borrow one hundred dollars but I was only one עד.
ed. I saw one pubic hair, you're testifying on half the matter.
You're testifying that this person is a קטן. katan. So of course
that can't combine.
But those seem two different places, so it means there are two
pubic hairs on that individual.
Well
first of all you can't combine the two you can't combine them
from different... places, number one. But even if you could, what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is, is that until now we've been saying
that I saw the full thing, but I saw it by myself
and you saw full thing and you saw it by yourself. Here
it's saying I saw half a thing by myself. So there's two
ways in which it's an incomplete עדות. eidus. It was only one
עד eid and not two עד ed and they only saw half
the manner. Okay, so that's what it says, it's חצי דבר וחצי
עדות. chatzi davar v'chatzi eidus. אלא אחד אומר שתים בגב ואחד אומר
שתים בכסל. ela echad omer shtayim begav v'echad omer shtayim bechasel. Fine.
One says I saw two pubic hairs here and one says I
saw two pubic hairs somewhere else. So each person עד eid testifies
that the person is an adult, but based on different evidence. Okay,
and that's like a hundred dollars on Monday and a hundred dollars
on Wednesday. Okay. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, אנא אמינא משמיה דעולא הלכה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה בין
בקרקעות ובין במטלטלין. ana amina mishmei d'Ulla halacha k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
bein b'karkaot u'vein b'metaltelin.
I said in the name of עולא Ulla that we rule like
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha whether by land or
by מטלטלין. metaltelin. ורבנן דאתו ממחוזא אמרי, v'rabbanan d'atu miMechuza amri,
but the rabbis who came from מחוזא Mechuza say, אמר רב זביד
משמיה דרב amar Rav Zevid mishmei d'Rav in the name of רב,
Rav, בקרקעות b'karkaot yes, we only rule like him by land, again
because then you're talking about the same object, אבל
לא במטלטלין, aval lo b'metaltelin, not by מטלטלין. metaltelin. So and רב
לטעמיה, Rav l'taameih, רב Rav goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב
הודאה אחר הודאה הודאה אחר הלואה מצטרפי. d'amar Rav hodaah achar hodaah
hodaah achar halvaah mitztarfi.
So רב Rav says, right, that it's only when they're talking about
the same thing do they combine. So what would be scenarios that
they're talking about the same thing other than קרקע? karka? There could
be cases when you say that ראובן Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars
from שמעון, Shimon, okay, here's a hundred dollars, here's your cash, let
me get my little dollar bills, okay, ראובן Reuven borrowed a hundred
dollars from שמעון. Shimon. Now what do the witnesses say? So one
witness says he admitted it, okay, הודאה. hodaah. And this witness says
he admitted it on Monday. And this witness says he admitted it
on Tuesday. Okay, now in that case, they could be talking about
the same thing, because both Monday and Tuesday he could be admitting
to the same hundred dollars. Okay, so the same way we agree
by קרקע, karka, we rule by קרקע, karka, we would also rule
like it by מטלטלין metaltelin if they are or could be talking
about the same actual event. So if both say that there was
an admission, maybe they both times ראובן Reuven was admitting, okay, to
the same hundred dollars. Okay, so דאמר רב, d'Rav amar, הודאה אחר
הודאה או הודאה אחר הלואה מצטרפי, hodaah achar hodaah o hodaah achar
halvaah mitztarfi,
or if I say, if this witness says on Monday I actually
witnessed the loan, witnessed the loan, and this witness says on Tuesday
he admitted the loan to me. Okay, then they could be talking
about the same loan. So then it could combine, right, because what
he admitted on Tuesday, what ראובן Reuven admitted on Tuesday, was that
he had borrowed money the day before. That would combine. הודאה
אחר
הלואה מצטרפי. hodaah achar halvaah mitztarfi. הלואה אחר הלואה או הלואה אחר
הודאה לא מצטרפי. halvaah achar halvaah o halvaah achar hodaah lo mitztarfi.
But if
he said a loan on Monday and he said I saw the
money borrowed on Tuesday, okay,
right,
in this case they're talking about different events. That's הלואה אחר הלואה.
halvaah achar halvaah. Or if he says on Monday he admitted it
to me
and he says on Tuesday I saw the loan. So then what
he admitted on Monday was something else. So in that case since
they're talking about different things they don't combine. Okay, so what רב
Rav is saying is, we only rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha when it's the same plot of land, or
it's a loan, but they could be talking about the same loan.
But when they're clearly talking about a different loan they don't combine.
Okay, אבל הלואה אחר הלואה לא מצטרפי. aval halvaah achar halvaah lo
mitztarfi. אשכחיה רב
נחמן בר יצחק לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. ashkacheih Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak l'Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua. So he found רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע. Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua. אמר ליה מאי שנא הלואה
אחר הלואה דלא? amar leih mai shna halvaah achar halvaah d'lo?
Why does a loan after a loan not work? דמנה דקחזי האי
לאו קחזי האי. d'maneh d'kahazi hai lav k'hazi hai. The loan that
one witness saw is not the loan that the other witness saw.
So הודאה אחר הודאה נמי. hodaah achar hodaah nami. So even if
they were one heard an admission on Monday and one heard it
on Tuesday, it's also they shouldn't combine. דמנה דקמודי קמיה האי לאו
קמודי קמיה האי. d'maneh d'kamodei kamey hai lav kamodei kamey hai.
The money that was admitted before the first witness is not the
money that was admitted before the second witness. Now the point is,
the point here is maybe, meaning הלואה אחר הלואה halvaah achar halvaah
you know it's talking about a different loan. הודאה אחר הודאה hodaah
achar hodaah it seems like רב's Rav's position was, if they're talking
about different days that he admitted, we can combine it because maybe
he's admitting to the same loan on two different days. But the
response seemed to be, but you don't know for sure that he's
admitting to the same loan. So if you need for us to
rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha to combine
them that they're talking about the same thing, how do we allow
an admission after an admission unless we know they're talking about the
same thing? actual same loan that he's admitting to. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, working with this idea that you have to
know for sure to combine it, it's not enough that it's a
possibility. He says maybe they say that's exactly what he's talking about.
אמר ליה דאמר ליה להאי בתרא בהאי מנא דאודי ליה קמך אודי
ליה נמי קמי פלוני. Amar lei d'amar lei l'hai batra b'hai mana
d'odi lei kamach odi lei nami kamei ploni. Oh,
okay, maybe the case is they know he's talking about the same
loan cause when he admitted on Tuesday to the second witness, he
said this loan I'm admitting to you today, yesterday I admitted to
the same loan before a different witness. So therefore we know he's
talking about the same loan. So the גמרא Gemara says אכתי, achti,
nevertheless, still say בתרא ידע קמא לא ידע. batra yada kama lo
yada. Okay,
but the second guy knew it was the same loan, the first
guy didn't know it was the same loan. Now the question is
why should that matter? We as בית דין Beis Din know it
was the same loan, right? Why he we're now making it much
more, many more criteria. It has to definitely be the same loan
and each witness has to know that they're talking about the same
loan the other one was being talked to. It's not just we
as בית דין Beis Din have to combine the pieces. The witnesses
themselves have to know that we're talking about the same loan. Okay,
why the גמרא Gemara is assuming this I don't know. So the
גמרא Gemara says דהדר אזיל אמר ליה לקמא האי מנא דאודי ליה
קמך אודי ליה נמי קמי פלוני. D'hadar azil amar lei l'kama hai
mana d'odi lei kamach odi lei nami kamei ploni. Okay, so
on Tuesday after he admitted to the second witness and said by
the way this loan I'm admitting to you I admitted to the
first witness on Monday, then he goes back on Tuesday to the
first witness and say that loan I admitted to you yesterday I
just now admitted to a different witness today. So this seems crazy.
רב Rav was never saying that you have to have each witness
know what the other witness was testified to, but the גמרא Gemara
here wants to limit רב Rav and say if you want to
make it like קרקע karka you have to be definitely certain we're
talking about the same loan and each witness has to know that
we're talking about the same loan. Okay, so אמר ליה תנוח דעתך
שהנחת את דעתי. Amar lei tanuach da'atach she'henachta es da'ati. Ah,
you should have it easy because you set my mind at rest.
I don't know why it's setting your mind at rest, this seems
so complicated. By the way, I would also say that if you
wanted to say that they both have to know it's talking about
the same loan, the easier way you would do it, rather than
saying I went and told each witness this is the same one
I blah blah blah, I would just give the particulars. When I
speak to witness number one I would say on December 21st at
12:00 PM in this location I borrowed $100 from this person and
I would give the exact same particulars to the other witness. And
then we know we're talking about the same loan. Why make it
so complicated that I had to tell him it was the same
thing I sold to the other guy and I go back to
the other guy? So I don't really get it. But now the
גמרא is trying to really limit this position of when you would
combine the testimonies. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so let's just wrap this
up. מאי ניחותא? Mai nichusa? Why is this so good? דרבא ואיתימא
רב ששת שדא ביה נרגא De'Rava v'isaima Rav Sheshes shada bei narga
because רבא, Rava, some say רב ששת Rav Sheshes threw like a
wrench in it. לאו היינו הודאה אחר הלואה? Lav hainu hoda'ah achar
halva'ah? So if you say this that you have to go back
and inform so everybody knows what everybody else heard, so even in
a case of an admission after a loan, one witness says I
saw the loan on Monday and the other said he admitted it
to me on Tuesday, according to this you'd have to go back
and say to the first witness by the way the loan you
saw yesterday I just admitted to the other witness on Tuesday. You'd
have to add this whole crazy complicated structure into this case. Okay
and then like why are we even bothering you know distinguishing the
cases? אמר ליה היינו דשמיע לי עלייכו, Amar lei hainu d'shmiah li
alaichu, so ah he says that explains why I've heard about you
guys. דרמיתו דיקלי וזקיפיתו להו. D'ramisu diklei v'zakifisu lehu. First you basically
chop down a tree in order to use it as building construction
and then we're about to build the house and you take the
tree back and you plant it again. So meaning you gave me
this beautiful answer and then you said wait that's not a good
answer I just gave you because that makes everything so whatever complicated.
Okay, anyway. Anyway this is a way of trying to limit the
פסק psak of רבא Rava and say was it רבא Rava we
were dealing with or רב? Rav? רב, Rav, to limit the פסק
psak of רב Rav to say that it has to be like
קרקע karka and so much, which is what רב Rav said, and
so much like קרקע karka that every עד eid has to know
that they were heard the admission of what the other עד eid
had also heard. All right, although clearly רב's Rav simple ruling is
as long as it's possible they're talking about the same thing we
combine it. But when they're definitely talking about a different thing we
don't combine it. That was the simple ruling of רב. Rav. Let's
read one more line,
wrap this up. נהרדעי אמרי. Nahardai amri. נהרדעי Nahardai says בין הודאה
אחר הודאה בין הודאה אחר הלואה בין הלואה אחר הלואה בין הלואה
אחר הודאה, Bein hoda'ah achar hoda'ah bein hoda'ah achar halva'ah bein halva'ah
achar halva'ah bein halva'ah achar hoda'ah,
however you have it, loan after loan, admission after admission, whatever, מצטרפין
mitztarfin they combine. Meaning it doesn't have to be like קרקע. karka.
Even if it's clearly different events, one says on Monday I saw
a loan and the other says on Tuesday I saw a loan,
they still combine. Okay, כמאן? keman? Like who? כרבי יהושע בן קרחה,
K'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Karcha, like a straight ruling like רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Karcha no distinctions. We always combine two different
witnesses even on different
events if the end... The result is that he owes a hundred
dollars. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, עדות המוכחשת, Eidut hamokhashat, okay,
I think so we'll end here. All right, so we'll stop here,
we will continue with this tomorrow.